Hey everyone, and thanks for jumping
back into the macroverse.
Today, we're going to talk about the
upcoming FOMC meeting occurring
tomorrow, and when the Federal Reserve
is likely going to raise interest rates.
If you guys like the content, make sure
you subscribe to the channel, give the
video a thumbs up, and check out the
sale on ITC Premium at
intothecryptoverse.com.
As a reminder, we do have the first
Investing Through the Cycles Conference
ITC coming up in November. Make sure you
guys check that out. We've got a lot of
great speakers already lined up, and
we'll be we will be announcing more
speakers in the coming weeks. We've
already got
several great speakers. I'm sure you
guys know all of them, but go take a
look on the website, and I look forward
to seeing you guys there.
So,
the sort of the the the big question
right now in the room is is the Fed
going to raise rates, and if they do,
when are they going to raise rates?
There have been some banks that have
come out and have said suggested that
they think the Fed's going to raise
interest rates tomorrow on July 29th.
My guess is that the Fed will keep rates
constant
tomorrow,
but raise rates likely in September.
And I want to talk about kind of how
that would fit the narratives that we've
been talking about.
At the end of the day,
you know, price follows, or sorry,
narrative follows price, not the other
way around, but it would make a lot of
sense
in thinking about how this business
cycle is is likely going to continue to
play out. So, if you go look at at
interest rates, right? You can see that
the Fed started raising rates back in,
you know, 2022, and they continued to
raise rates and then they kind of held
constant in 2023 and 2024 and then they
lowered rates three times in 2024 and
they lowered rates three times in 2025.
And
now the question is is well, are they
going to raise rates again?
One thing to consider is the long end of
the yield curve.
When you look at the 10-year yield, I've
talked about this for a long time that
the 10-year yield would likely be
heading back up to the high in October
of 2023.
The 30-year yield already did that and
my guess is that it's going to break out
soon and that the 10-year yield will
start to follow it. Now, what I think is
likely going to happen is that the Fed
is not going to raise rates tomorrow. If
they do raise rates tomorrow, then that
will come as somewhat of a surprise to
me. That doesn't mean that they can't
raise rates, I just think it's very
unlikely.
And if you look at a chart like this, it
would all make sense if they don't raise
rates looking at this chart and let me
explain.
The 30-year yield looks like it wants to
move higher, right? Like it's been
moving up against this level for years.
This
5.1 5.2%
level.
You can see it it keeps going down after
testing it, but it keeps going right
back up to that level and it keeps on
putting in higher lows.
I think what's going to happen
is the Fed will likely hold rates
and I could see sort of the the bond
vigilantes coming out and saying, "No,
raising rates is needed right now." And
you could argue that raising rates is
needed according to the bond market,
perhaps because labor market is still
relatively okay and there's this fear
that inflation might start to come back.
Now, in the short term, in the short
term inflation, you know, hasn't like
over the last month you could argue all
right, inflation wasn't a huge issue. We
actually saw inflation come back down,
but let's walk through this for a
minute.
Inflation went up from 2. 2.4%
to four over 4.1%
in just a few months and then it had a
big drop back down at 3.4 3.5. Now, that
looks good, right? That it's heading
back in the right direction and you
couple that with energy, if you look at
like XLE, energy when that print came
out was all the way down here.
Yeah, you know, at around 52 53. This
was XLE. But, the problem is from a
technical perspective, maybe XLE was
just back testing this and if energy is
poised to go higher
because there because the markets aren't
crap like the the the labor market is
fine, then the only you could argue that
energy could still be a headwind in in
the short term and thereby making
inflation a larger risk. Now, when you
look at the labor market, if you look at
initial claims, we just put in the
lowest initial claims that I think I've
seen. I mean, it was 187,000.
I don't even know the last time we were
at that level, right? 187?
I mean, when is the last time that that
happened?
You'd have to go back decades, I
believe. So,
if if initial claims are low and and
energy is starting to show a little bit
of a bid again, then you run the risk
with inflation
that inflation might start to creep back
up. Now, you could say, "Well, this is a
pretty nice drop."
And it is, but you know, there have been
other times where you had a big move up
by inflation for it to then drop back
down, but then it accelerated once again
to the upside. So,
I think what the bond market
is telling us
is is it saying that
the issue right now is not with the
labor market. The issue is with
inflation. And if you look at the
unemployment rate
If you look at the unemployment rate
it's 4.2, right? It's actually been
generally trending down
since November of 2025, right? So,
perhaps the market is saying, "Look, the
labor market's fine,
but inflation is kind of a concern. And
if the Fed does not hike tomorrow, which
I don't think they will, it might be the
perfect excuse for the 10-year yield to
head back up to 5% and it could be the
perfect excuse for the 30-year yield to
break through 5.2%, which has been the
level that it's been rejected at since
2023.
So, when you think about all this, does
it make sense in terms of the market
views that we provided? Well, the first
thing I will say is this. Think about
when the Fed cut rates in or sorry, when
the Fed raised rates. No, when the Fed
cut rates. Think about when the Fed cut
rates in 2024 and 2025. When did they
start? Did they start in July?
No.
They started in September.
If you look at the Fed funds rate
in 2024 and 2025, the cuts started in
September of '24
and September of '25.
So, I would say it would almost be
unprecedented, at least in recent
history, that they would start raising
rates in the summer for the first time.
I would argue they're most likely going
to hold rates constant
and then raise rates in September. And
the reason why is because I think I
think if they hold rates constant, which
is what I think they're going to do, the
the bond vigilantes are going to revolt.
The long end of the yield curve is going
to go up and then the Fed's going to
realize, oh,
maybe we need to hike rates, especially
if if the energy trade starts to come
back.
So, that's kind of how I think this is
going to happen. And the reason why it
makes sense is because we've talked as
well about the S&P likely getting a
correction in, you know, in um
the sort of the back end of the of the
or the second half of the midterm year
and it would be in line with prior
corrections, like when we had prior
corrections. If you look at at 2022, you
had a correction in stocks starting in
August. If you look at 2018, you had a
correction by stocks starting in
September. And if you look at 2014, you
had a correction in stocks starting in
um like September time frame. So, you
have three midterm years in recent
history. One of those midterm years,
2018, Trump was also president.
And in all three cases, you have a 10 to
20% drop by stocks.
So, think about it. If the Fed does not
raise rates and the bond market the bond
market revolts, long end goes up, that'd
be a good sort of a good catalyst for a
potential correction in the back half of
the year. Look at what happened in 2023.
The bond market was long end of the
yield curve is going up and there was a
correction starting in late July.
And it was about a 10% drop. So, what
I'm saying is I I we're about to see a
10 to 20% drop in stocks. Now, that
doesn't in the stock in the S&P. That
doesn't mean it has to start today. You
could potentially see another all-time
high first. Again, in a couple of the
midterm years, it didn't even start
until August or September.
So, I'm not saying it has to start yet,
but what I am saying is that if the Fed
does not raise rates, the bond market
will likely revolt given where the labor
market is and given where inflation is.
And it will then likely force the Fed to
raise rates a little bit later this
year.
Now, look at the market probabilities,
right? Look at the uh the FedWatch tool
over here. Uh we'll reload this just to
make sure I have the most recent data.
I'm not sure when I I last looked at it.
But, according to this,
the Fed only has, you know, about a
29.4%
chance they're going to raise rates
tomorrow. It would be quite a shock for
the Fed to raise rates. Normally, when
you have like this high of a
probability, they tend to go with the uh
the the the the actual like, you know,
what it what the markets are thinking.
Remember, the markets tell the Fed what
to do, not the other way around. The Fed
follows the two-year yield.
It is and this is something really
important, I think, for everyone to sort
of take note of. If you look at at
interest rates, if you look at interest
rates and you overlay the two-year yield
onto the chart,
right? Now, let's actually make this the
same scale just cuz I want you to um
kind of see like what it looks like
relative to uh you know, relative to the
other metric we're tracking here. The
Fed tracks the two-year yield. So, look
at this.
Wait, let me flip this over to a monthly
scale. Um but, you can see that the the
two-year yield, the purple line, will
move and then the Fed will follow,
right? You can see in 2021, the two-year
yield started going up and then the Fed
followed. And then the two-year yield
was going down, the Fed followed. But,
now look what's happening. The two-year
yield is going up. It's above where the
Fed funds rate is now. And so, the
argument is that with the Fed funds rate
where it is, we're no longer
sufficiently restrictive.
In order to be restrictive,
the argument is that the Fed would need
to raise rates.
Now, where does the market think the Fed
will raise rates to?
Well, they think it'll raise rate
they'll raise rates to 4.25% by
December.
What's interesting about 4.25%
is that's
that's where the two-year yield is,
basically 4.1, 4.2%.
So,
the market is telling the Fed they need
to raise rates.
But the Fed, according to the markets,
is not really going to raise rates this
month. So, what I think's going to
happen is that they won't raise rates,
the bond market revolts, long end heads
higher, you get some type of correction
in the stock market kind of in the
August, September starting in August,
September time frame. You get a couple
of rate hikes. It has that correction in
the stock market. You see Bitcoin
um drop even more, going to its market
cycle bottom. Remember, Bitcoin normally
bottoms in the back half of midterm
years, in the back half of the back half
of midterm years, normally in the fourth
quarter.
This is the narrative that you need. Not
that you need one, but if you needed
one, this is the only one that you need.
And then perhaps people get freaked out
because they're like, "Oh no, the Fed's
raising rates." But remember guys, if
the Fed's raising rates and they're not
breaking anything, then it just means
the economy's fine. Now, people might
freak out in the short term,
but the economy would arguably be okay
at least in that in that brief window.
There is some precedent for the Fed
raising rates after a cutting cycle. If
you look in the '90s in the dot-com era,
the Fed raised rates in in the sort of
the mid-'90s, they lowered, and then
they ended up raising it again. I think
they raised like seven or eight times
before they finally broke something. So,
you could argue that one rate hike isn't
going to necessarily change anything. I
I yes, it's going to be bad for some of
the more speculative stuff like altcoins
and whatnot, but that most of that stuff
has no business existing anyways. Not
saying all of it, but a lot of it has no
businesses existing anyways, and a lot
of those companies are now finding out
that, you know, they only existed during
loose monetary policy, and now that this
higher for longer stuff is going on,
they're just no longer able to survive
in this type of of market environment.
So, only the stronger things will
survive, and that's why you've seen this
flight to safety throughout various
asset classes. That's why you've seen,
you know, mega-cap tech stocks
outperform micro-cap stocks.
That's why you've seen Bitcoin
outperform altcoins. Now, I've seen some
people say, "Well, what about Bitcoin
dominance? It hasn't moved." But,
remember, when you actually exclude
stablecoins,
which you should,
I don't get why more people don't. If
you exclude stables, dominance is still
going up. It's just that if you include
stables, it's not going up. But, the
reason why dominance is struggling is
because stablecoin dominance has been
moving up a lot this year, right? I
mean, stablecoin dominance since October
of 2025 has gone from 6% to about 12%.
Over 13% actually, right? So, stablecoin
dominance basically doubled. So, that's
the reason why dominance in recent
months hasn't been going up as much, but
when you exclude stablecoins, it is
going up.
It's been steadily climbing for a long
time. So, the flight to safety is there,
and the reason it's there is because
monetary policy is still remaining
restrictive. And the reason monetary
policy is restrictive is just simply
because there's not really a great
reason for looser monetary policy when
you have initial claims putting in the
lowest levels you've seen in years, for
in decades, and the unemployment rate
trending down for the last year, while
energy prices are still elevated. I know
oil has had a big drop, right? There's
more. There's obviously a lot more to
the energy trade than oil.
Um
There's just a lot of con- There's the
geopolitical conflict. I I think there's
just a lot of uncertainty in the air,
especially as the macro goes, and that's
how I think this is going to play out.
We'll talk a lot more about this at the
conference in November. So, make sure
you guys
uh get a ticket. Uh we will be raising
the prices of those tickets in in just a
few weeks. So, if you guys want to go um
and you want to grab your ticket before
then, make sure you do so. I'm looking
forward to seeing you guys there. Thank
you guys for tuning in. Subscribe, give
the video thumbs up, and I'll see you
guys next time. Bye.